A country of 20 million people recorded 1
million deaths during a deadly pandemic.
在一次致命瘟疫中 一个国家中的两千万人中有一百万人死亡
More than half of these deaths had
been vaccinated against the disease,
在死亡人数中有一半接种了针对这种疾病的疫苗
but this rate was only marginally
different to the remaining population.
但在幸存的人当中这个（疫苗接种的）比例只有很小的出入
This led many to conclude that vaccination had
had no effect on the mortality rate. In fact,
这将会导出疫苗针对降低死亡率无效的结论
it appeared that being vaccinated even increased
the chance of death. However a statistician put
实际上 看起来似乎接种反而增加了死亡风险
these deaths into three different age groups,
and found the opposite trend. Within each group,
然而一位统计学家将这些死亡数分在三个不同的年龄组中 由此发现了相反的趋势
those vaccinated were far less likely to die from
the disease. This apparent contradiction is known
在每一组中 接种者的死亡风险都远远更低
as "Simpson's Paradox", where the aggregate of all
the data shows a trend that is opposite to that
这个明显的矛盾被称为辛普森悖论 它强调所有数据展现的趋势可能和分组数据截然相反
when broken down into groups. It's usually the
result of other factors not shown on the graph.
它通常是由没有在图表中展示的因素导致的
In this example, it is that being old
independently increases the likelihood of death,
在这个例子中 年长因素独立地对死亡风险和受接种概率有贡献
and the likelihood of being vaccinated. So
in this case, using only the combined data
所以此情况下 仅仅使用总体的数据
to draw conclusion about the vaccine's
effectiveness would be incorrect.
得到有关疫苗有效性的结论是不正确的